<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Crisp's envy detected and folly manifested herein and the addition following by R.R. being an answer to his book entituled, The fourth part of Babels, &amp;c. / by J.F. Junior.</title>
            <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18777444</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18777444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1653:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Thomas Crisp's envy detected and folly manifested herein and the addition following by R.R. being an answer to his book entituled, The fourth part of Babels, &amp;c. / by J.F. Junior.</title>
                  <author>Field, John, 1652-1723.</author>
                  <author>Richardson, Richard, 1623?-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin CLark ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Postscript signed: R. Richardson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bevan-Naish Collection.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Thomas, 17th cent. --  Fourth part of Babel's builders unmask'd.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108319:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Criſp's</hi> ENVY DETECTED AND FOLLY MANIFESTED Herein, and the Addition following by <hi>R.R.</hi> BEING AN ANSWER To his BOOK <hi>Entituled,</hi> The FOURTH PART of <hi>Babel's,</hi> &amp;c</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 27.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Though thou ſhould bray a Fool in a Mortar among Wheat with a Peſtil, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wrath is cruel, and Anger is out-ragious; but who is able to ſtand againſt Envy?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 11.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lo, the wicked bend their Bow, they make ready their Arrow upon their ſtring, that they may privily ſhoot at the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in heart.</p>
               <p>But, Behold the Eye of the Lord is upon them that fear him, upon them that hope in his mercy, to deliver their Soul from Death, and to keep them alive in Famine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By one that according to his meaſure prays for the peace of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and proſperity of</hi> Sion, <hi>which God is making the</hi> beauty of Holineſs, and praiſe of the whole Earth, <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Rage of all her Enemies, and fury of her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi> Junior.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin-Clark</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> Bookſeller, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:108319:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108319:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi>'s Envy Detected and Folly Manifeſted herein, and the Addition following by <hi>R. R.</hi> being an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his Book, Entituled, <hi>The Fourth Part of</hi> Babel<hi>'s, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UPon the 20th of the Firſt Month, 1681/2. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi>'s hand a Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Fourth Part of Babel's Builders,</hi> &amp;c. which he told me I was concerned in, which upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal I find my name, or the Letters for it is mentioned near thirty times. And I therein termed and charged by him ſeveral times <hi>to be a falſe Witneſs,</hi> and with <hi>grand falſhood</hi> and called <hi>Inquiſition Officer,</hi> and ſuch like. All which Reproaches I might and willingly could bear, and forbear thus to mention, and Rejoyce that the Lord hath counted me worthy to be of that little number or Remnant, which are Reproached for the name of Chriſt, knowing that the Spirit of Glory and of God reſteth upon ſuch. And they and I have indeed cauſe to rejoyce, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as Chriſt Exhorted; it being <hi>falſly ſpoken</hi>—though this was of old the Lot or portion of ſeveral of God's Servants, and alſo of his People: for remember <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.8. <hi>Mine Enemies Reproach me all the day, and they that are mad againſt me, are Sworn againſt me.</hi> And did not <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> reproach <hi>Iſrael</hi> in daies paſt, and yet ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſaid to me, go up againſt this Land and deſtroy it.</hi> And for my part I ſhall leave it (to the manifeſtation of God's Spirit in every ones heart thereby to judge whether or no the ſame Spirit that led <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108319:3"/>(ſo to <hi>Reproach</hi> Iſrael <hi>and the living God</hi>) hath not entred <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi> and his Adherents and Abettors; though they may as <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> ſay (or pretend its the Lord and it's his Cauſe they ſtand for, and its his Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Conſcience they would Exalt; but bleſſed be God in and by the bleſſed and divine Light of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (which a Remnant was firſt turned to, in which they have believed and have fellowſhip with God and oue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) they clearly ſee, that it's not his <hi>Government,</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt's,</hi> &amp;c. that they would Exalt, (notwithſtanding their pretences) but the Rule and Government of him, who Rules in the Hearts <hi>of the Children of Diſobedience,</hi> whoſe unfruitful <hi>Works of Darkneſs</hi> they are bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, though they Nick-name them; and would put off their corrupt droſs for pure Gold, guilding it over with a few fair words and fine Specches, by which they would delude and deceive the hearts of the ſimple; but bleſſed be God who hath ſo preſerved a Remnant in his fear, that from him they have receiv'd Wiſdom, and thereby are taught, not to buy, or receive though offered any of theſe mens corrupt Wares and falſe Doctrines; and I believe the time haſtens, in which they like their <hi>Brethren</hi> of old ſhall <hi>(becauſe no man buyeth her Merchandize any more) weep and mourn over their Mother Myſtery Babilon, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots and abominations of the Earth,</hi> that had as fair pretences, and as guilded a Cup, and as highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of her Seat, as <hi>T. C.</hi> and his Company are of theirs; and if they Repent not, I queſtion not, but they ſhall as ſurely be Judged, plagued and tormented as ſhe was: <hi>For ſtrong is the Lord that Judgeth her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Paper out of which he Collects what he takes occaſion, to charge me with <hi>falſhood</hi> and being <hi>a falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and draws his Concluſion from: that I am not a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, is a Paper which I had ſet down his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in, and to that had as in that which was Printed in <hi>S. Criſp</hi>'s Book ſet my name, as a Witneſs, in which Paper was theſe words he ſo charges upon me, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo often in his Book. I therefore thought meet here to ſet down a Copy of it, which he calls in his 18 page, J. F<hi>'s Bull of Excommunication againſt me,</hi> but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108319:3"/>why he calls it <hi>J. F</hi>'s he hath not told. It is as followeth, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Several years ſince as it doth and may appear by our Monthly-Meeting Book, <hi>Thomas Crisp</hi> and his Wife in the tender Love of God were viſited by Friends (in order to bring them unto a Sence of the Evil they had done in being Marryed by a Prieſt, for which there is no preſident nor Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the holy Scriptures of Truth,) for about<note n="*" place="margin">It's thought it was <hi>11</hi> Mo ths in the other, but if ſo it's a miſtake.</note> 
                     <hi>7</hi> Months, and his Wife did give in a paper into Friends, wherein ſhe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns that practice or thing, and the Spirit that led her thereunto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But her Husband did not come ſo far, as to Condemn it; notwithſtanding Friends viſits from time to time when they were all Clear, left viſiting of him, and be remained, and hath and doth unto this day, a man out of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Friends whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and fellowſhip ſtands in that Eternal Spirit which leads all them that are faithfull there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto to be all of one mind and to ſpeak the ſame thing, and by the ſame Spirit a remnant are joyned together in the ſame mind and in the ſame Judgment among whom there is no divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and theſe with the one mind and mouth glorify God, and Serve him, even the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with one mind and one accord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with <hi>Thomas Crisp</hi> nor his Doctrine which is as followeth. The 8th of the <hi>9</hi> month. <hi>1681.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Crisp</hi> ſaid that he had lately payed Tythes, and that the Spirit of God did or might allow him to pay Tythes or Marry by a Preiſt. And that by the ſame Spirit of God ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might be required not to pay them, or not do the ſame things.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Thomas Crisp</hi> ſpoke, the day and year aboue ſaid And Conſented to have it Writt and printed and took a Coppy of the aforeſaid words: <hi>Witneſs</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>John Feild, <hi>Junior.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And now I ſhall take ſome notice what <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith <hi>in his 4th part of</hi> Babels, <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 19. which is as followeth, <hi>And</hi> I. F. <hi>hath falſly aſſerted that</hi> T. C. <hi>did Evil, in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of his Marriage, alſo he ſays for which there is no Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the holy Scriptures for there is preſident and Command in Scripture for what</hi> T. C. <hi>did.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:108319:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> Obſerve the words of that paper which he calls mine, are as followeth <hi>T. C.</hi> and his Wife, in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Love of God, was viſited by Friends (in order to bring them to a Sence of the Evil they had done in being Marryed <hi>by a Prieſt</hi> whom he had diſown'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now <hi>T. C.</hi> a few lines after in the ſame 19. page ſaith, <hi>viz. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho it is commonly ſaid Marryed by Friends, but more properly before them; ſo was ours before the Prieſt, but not</hi> by him. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> How then hath, <hi>I. F.</hi> falſly Aſſerted, who ſaid Friends viſited him? <hi>viz.</hi> T. C. in order to bring him to a Sence of the Evil he had done in being marryed by a Prieſt; and if this was a falſe Aſſertion, and what thou did there be preſident and Command in Scripture for; why did thy Wife Condemn it? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thou in the 18. <hi>page diriding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls paying Tythes and Marrying by Prieſts black Sins, and in the</hi> 19. <hi>page ſayeſt it was thy principle,</hi> viz, <hi>to Marry by a Preiſt, or Pay Tythes, and in the ſame page thou ſayeſt thou was not Marryed by a Preiſt. Anſwer,</hi> Then not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy Principle, and what man of Reaſon or underſtanding thinkeſt will Regard ſuch a man that is not true to his own principle, what grand <hi>Hypocryſy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction</hi> and <hi>Babiloniſh Confuſion</hi> is this to ſay its thy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple to pay Tythes; and in the ſame page <hi>ſay, It was in requital of a kindneſs readily and freely granted by the Perſon to my ſelf and another Concerned, and not as Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. and yet ſay <hi>thou haſt lately paid Tythes.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> The Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which lays ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Houſe in the new Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, <hi>per l.</hi> as the Houſe is rated at for the Pariſh Prieſt calls that rate Tythes.</note> And yet behold he is an Abettor, of the true Chriſtian <hi>Quakers</hi> canſe, falſely ſo called. But come <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſhew me where <hi>J. F</hi>'s falſe Aſſertion is, and what Chapter or verſe in the Scripture there is either preſident or command for being Marryed by a prieſt? and then <hi>I. F.</hi> will confeſs he hath aſſerted falſely concerning thee in this thing, but I Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thy eyes will ſink in their holes before thou find that place though it be thy principle. Again, in <hi>the ſaid</hi> 19. <hi>pag.</hi> you ſay'ſt <hi>I Condeſcended to take my Wife</hi> in <hi>the preſence of a Preiſt</hi> [what need of ſuch a Condeſcention if there be preſident and Command in Scripture for what thou didſt] <hi>and Acquainted him</hi> that <hi>I did it not on any point of Religion but to Anſwer</hi> the Law. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> What is there no point of Religion in it, and yet preſident and Command in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108319:4"/>Scripture for it as thou ſayſt; but I affirm, Marriage is an Ordinance of God and Inſtituted by him in Paradice. Well <hi>Thomas,</hi> But if there was ſuch a care upon thee, to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Law, let's examine how thou haſt Anſwered that? ſeeing in <hi>pag.</hi> 15. Thou ſayſt, <hi>It's a wonder to me when I Conſider how many have been Encouraged to deny or refuſe Submiſſion to Authority, on pretence of Conſcience</hi>—Again, <hi>But for being Subject to the Magiſtrate for Conſcience ſake, that is accounted Submitting to the</hi> Pope [I think to ſpeake more to this wicked and falſe Aſſertion.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But doth not the Authority, Magiſtrates and Law, require more a great deal to be done, by Perſons that joyn in Matrimony or Marriage than thou Relates thou didſt Read the form of the Solemnization of Marriage in the Common Prayer Book, which all Prieſt's in Orders are obliged and bound by the Acts of Uniformity to do, and upon failure to be deprived of their Benefice <hi>ipſo facto</hi> as it dead; for the Common Prayer herein well and reaſonably provides, that the Banes ſhould be Asked or Publiſhed three ſeveral times in their Aſſemblies or Church (ſo call'd) that no Perſon might be deprived of their Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without their knowledge. And are they not to give their Troth, one to the other? and ſay <hi>thereto I plight my Troth.</hi> And yet ſaith the <hi>Man ſhould give unto the Woman a Ring, laying the ſame upon the Book with the Coſtomed Dutys to the Prieſt and Clark, and the Prieſt taking the Ring, ſhall deliver it to the Man, to put upon the fourth finger of the womans left hand. And the man holding the Ring there and taught by the Preiſt ſhall ſay, With this Ring I thee Wedd, with my Body I thee Worſhip, and with my World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goods I thee Endow,</hi> &amp;c. Now Conſider how <hi>T. C.</hi> hath Anſwered the Law and who they are that now may be Wondered at, and that are Guilty of Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if <hi>T. C.</hi> hath not thus done how he hath Anſwered the Law, been Submiſive and Subject to Authority, let the unprejudiced Judge.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> And let <hi>W. R. F. B. L. K.</hi> and ſuch that Abetts this man and his work, conſider if it was, thus practiſed by Friends in the beginning, or ſince thus, to Marry, and hav. a Ring, <hi>&amp;</hi> a Prieſt, which let <hi>T. C.</hi> if he will or can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he had; only I would deſire and adviſe him to remember what I ſaid to him at his Houſe about it, and what he then Anſwer'd; and this I would add. It ſeems he is not only againſt going before the Women to lay his Intention, but the men alſo, and is neither for laying his Intention of Marriage before either of them, neither once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> twice, but for doing it clandeſtinely.</note> And I deſire all tender hearted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108319:5"/>Friends, to whoſe hands theſe may come, to conſider whether this be as it was in the beginning (of Friends) what did they get a Preiſt and three or four of their Acquaintance, under pretence of Anſwering the Law and take one another before them as <hi>T. C.</hi> page 19. of Babels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaith he did, certainly nay, or did they declare their Intentions firſt to the People of God, and then take one another before a Meeting with the Conſent of Parents or Relations concerned, I hope they in whom any tenderneſs is, and whoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings are not wholy darkened, will ſee what Spirit this buſie and great Abettor of the Cauſe of <hi>W.R. J. W.</hi> and ſuch like is led by, who ſo highly commends <hi>the Charity and Chriſtian condeſcention of the Prieſt,</hi> that he ſaith in his Book page 19. <hi>its to much, there to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</hi> But he ſhews little, nay no Charity but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Enmity, when he moſt wickedly, falſly, and maliciouſly ſaith, <hi>That for being Subject to the Magiſtrate for Conſcience ſake is accounted (by Friends) Submitting to the Pope,</hi> much may be ſaid hereto, to ſhew his great <hi>Enmity</hi> and falſhood, and how he would hereby Stir up and Incenſe, the Magiſtrate againſt us eſpecially at this time when our Friends in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Briſtol</hi> and elſewhere lye under hard and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Sufferings, but let this Serve to give a Relliſh of the mans Spirit and who it is ſetts him to Work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whoſe preſent looſe principle never will lead him to loſe any thing for Chriſt's ſake, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
            <p>But page 19, 20. <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>But it is obſervable, that about the time that</hi> J. F. <hi>publiſhed this againſt me</hi> Ellis Hookes <hi>was dead (the Clark of the Marriages) and had left a conſiderable Eſtate; and 'tis ſaid, much of it was gained by Fees and Gratuities about Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, which was more gain to him than to ſeveral Prieſts in</hi> London <hi>put together. This ſo profitable an Office (as is thought)</hi> J. F. <hi>wanting or coveting, might be glad of this opportunity to gain the favour of</hi> G. F. &amp;c. <hi>Alſo to make others be afraid of being ſo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108319:5"/>if they ſhould let others have the profits of their Marriage Certificates,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi> ſeeing thou hast brought <hi>Ellis Hooks's</hi> name in publick Print, who is dead, and cannot now Anſwer for himſelf to thy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating and Slandering Tongue; and thou ſayſt. <hi>That</hi> E. Hooks <hi>left a conſiderable Eſtate, and it's ſaid much of it was gained by Fees, and Gratuities about Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages;</hi> and then ſaith, <hi>Which was more gain to him than to ſeveral Prieſts in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>put together.</hi> I do charge <hi>T. Criſp</hi> to mention and bring forth their Names in publick Print, that hath ſaid this of <hi>Ellis Hooks,</hi> and prove that he hath gotten his conſiderable Eſtate that he left behind him <hi>by Fees and Gratuities about Marriages,</hi> and now <hi>T. C.</hi> is poſitive, when he ſaith <hi>which,</hi> was <hi>more gain to him than ſeveral Prieſts in</hi> London <hi>put together.</hi> This I charge him again to prove, if he can, concerning <hi>E. H.</hi> But let this foul mouth'd Buſie body <hi>T. C.</hi> ask <hi>E. H</hi>'s Brother the Councellor, if his Father did not give him an Eſtate; beſides, it's known to the Friends of Truth in this City, that <hi>E. H.</hi> was a <hi>Stationer;</hi> and by his Induſtry in that Employ, gained a conſiderable part of his Eſtate; and other lawful and conſiderable Employs he had which augmented his Eſtate But <hi>T. C</hi>'s Envy againſt Truth and its Children is ſo large, and he in it ſo reſtleſs, that therein he abuſes and belies both the Living and the Dead.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> What an Obſervable matter this is, that <hi>Ellis Hooks</hi> was dead, the Clark of the Marriages at this time and left a Conſiderable Eſtate. What then? why, <hi>Thomas Crisp</hi> thereby hath gotten an oppertunity out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his malitious heart to vent ſome of his Envious thoughts and malicious words againſt <hi>J. Feild</hi> and ſays (if he may be believed) much (<hi>viz</hi> of <hi>E. H.</hi> Eſtate) <hi>was gained</hi> by <hi>fees and gratuities as its ſaid,</hi> this is like his Brother <hi>W. R.</hi> whoſe Example he herein follows who often ſaith <hi>if report</hi> be <hi>true:</hi> But ſaith <hi>T. C. This ſo proffita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an Office, as (its thought)</hi> J. F. <hi>wanting, or Coveting, might be glad of this opportunity, to gain the favour of</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As (its thought) <hi>Aye,</hi> but had <hi>T. C.</hi> or any of his Abettors or Informers ſo ſaid I ſhould have told them it was a palpable untruth and baſe thought, as its both a baſe and unworthy Action of <hi>T. Criſp</hi> thus publickly to defame and Scandalize me in print, upon an Evil thought, this is not like the Spirit of Chriſt but I can Expect no better of him, that may well be compared to a rageing wave of the Sea caſting up mire and dirt. But bleſſed be God <hi>J. F.</hi> hath through the Lord's bleſſing, and his Endeavour that whereby he hath hitherto, honeſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for himſelf and his Family, without either Covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or receiving that which is anothers by griping or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108319:6"/>any man and can ſay with the Apoſtle his own hands have miniſtred to his neceſſity, and he hath not been chargeable unto any. And hopes he ſhall unto the End of his dayes, through the Aſſiſtance of the Lord and by his grace manifeſt himſelf to be an honeſt man, though not ſo rich as <hi>T. C.</hi> that writes thus maliciouſly againſt him, for whom his prayer is and ſhall be (if it be the Lords will, that he and ſuch as he) may come to ſee the Evil Work he is about and Repent of it before it be to late.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. C.</hi> page 18 deridingly ſaith, <hi>As for thoſe black ſins (of paying Tythes and marrying by Prieſts) ſo often charged on</hi> T. C. <hi>by</hi> S. C. <hi>and his Confederates (on which</hi> J. F. <hi>hath grounded his Bull of Excommunication againſt me) and ſay they have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I deſire the Bull of Excommunication as he Scoffingly, and maliciouſly calls that paper may by the Chriſtian and unprejudiced Reader, be well peruſed to See if they can find that any thing therein deſerves, ſuch a Scornfull name, for he is not therein Curſt, that being who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and is for ever utterly diſowned by us, (the true Chriſtians call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Quakers.</hi>) What, <hi>Thomas,</hi> muſt wee ſay we do own Perſons, that are not of us, and have Unity with them that thou gives, this frightful terme of <hi>Bull of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> to that Innocent paper, that I believe and am fully Satisfied was writt and given forth to manifeſt, and tell others, that knew thee not ſo well as thy Neighbours do, what thou art, and what thy practice hath been, for peradventure, they might think thee by thy fair words to be that, thou art not, and is it not pity but ſuch ſhould be better informed. Well, <hi>Thomas,</hi> my deſire is thou mayſt Repent of <hi>theſe black Sins</hi> of Envy and Falſhood, and not encourage others to do the ſame, leſt thou become guilty of their Sins alſo.</p>
            <p>Here followeth a ſhort Collection of ſome of <hi>Thomas Criſp</hi>'s many Falſhoods or Untruths, with ſhort Notes thereupon to <hi>ſhew his Envy and detect his Folly</hi> in uſing my name ſo often, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and repeating ſome Sentences of mine (relating to Friends Unity, and being of one mind an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108319:6"/>judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) in all which he leaves out the material words, as apparently as if a wicked Atheiſt ſhould ſay he would prove from the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. That he ſaid, <hi>There is no God;</hi> he ſhould leave out theſe words, <hi>viz. (The Fool hath ſaid in his heart there is)</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner hath this unfair Adverſary dealt with me, as I with the Lord's help ſhall ſhew.</p>
            <p>In the 20 <hi>p. And for</hi> J. F. <hi>to ſay their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſtands in the Eternal Spirit, it is falſe, ſaith</hi> T. C.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> But who, <hi>Thomas,</hi> doſt think will believe thee, for my part I ſhall not, neither take thy word herein who art ſo Hypocritical and unfaithful, as to act contrary to thy own principle (as I have before ſhewed.) And I do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that our (and all faithful Friends and true Chriſtians) Unity and Fellowſhip, does ſtand in the Eternal Spirit of God, and that it is grand falſhood and untruth in thee to ſay otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>P. 18. T. C. ſaith, <hi>As for thoſe black ſins (of paying Tythes and Marrying by Prieſts, ſo often charged on</hi> T. C. <hi>by</hi> S. C. <hi>and his Confederates (on which</hi> J. F. <hi>hath grounded his Bull of Excommunication againſt me.) And ſay they have no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Why, <hi>Thomas,</hi> doſt thou ſay thou haſt Unity with us that thou art ſo Angry at that Paper thou calleſt my Bull, as to uſe my Name ſeven times in a page, and more than four times ſeven in thy three Sheets and half of <hi>Babel,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe that paper ſaith thou, remaineſt a man out of the Unity of Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Prethee <hi>Thomas</hi> is this a breach of that Reveaſed will of God thou ſpeakeſt of, <hi>p.</hi> 12. to ſay, thou remaineſt a man out of the Unity of Friends, that thou art ſo Angry, to term and compare me to an <hi>Inquiſition Officer.</hi> This is not the way to convince me, that the Spirit of Chriſt in the Heart moves thee thus to write, or rather ſcribble againſt me and Friends, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy Conceits are of promoting and contending for the Rule of the Goſpel of the Spirit of Chriſt in the heart.<note n="*" place="margin">I ſuppoſe you may know whoſe Phraſes theſe are.</note> And my deſire is that I and all tender-hearted honeſt Friends may never know the Rule nor Government of that Spirit thou art led and inſtigated by; thus to vent thy malicious words, prating like ſome of old againſt the Truth.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:108319:7"/>
            <p>And in the 19 page T. C. <hi>ſaith, And on other diſcourſe with</hi> J.F. <hi>the next day per ceiving he intended to publiſh it, did ſay hemight do it—therefore conſented to his writing thoſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Yes, <hi>Thomas,</hi> and to the Printing of them too (thou conſented) otherwiſe, for all what thou ſayſt, thou perceived (I Intended) it had never been Printed, as it was. And I queſtion not but thou and <hi>P.E.</hi> then in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with thee, knows and may remember, that thou ſaid (vauntingly) it would cover or hide but a little ſpot of the Beaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and took a Copy of it with thee.</p>
            <p>And in the 21 page T.C. ſaith, <hi>If you were in the Eternal Spirit as</hi> J.F. <hi>falſly ſays, your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity would not ſtand in forms and Ceremonies and Orders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Prethee, <hi>Thomas,</hi> who ever ſaid, it did? ſure it was not <hi>J. F.</hi> that hath been ſo often termed falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſaying it was in the Eternal Spirit; don't quarrel and fight thus with thy own Shadow or ſancy, who in thy <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> Spirit, would inſinuate as if Friends Unity were in Ceremonies and Orders, which we deny, though we own the order of the Goſpel and Law of Life, and what are the products of the Spirit of Truth, and that which it leads into and tends to vertue and good Report, and to the Teſtifying againſt vice and looſeneſs, and that which would bring an ill Report (though thou mayſt ſcoffingly call them <hi>G. F</hi>'s Orders and Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and though to our grief ſome, (who for want of keeping in the holy fear of God, and a diligent waiting upon him in low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of mind, therein to be guided by his Wiſdom and Councel) have not ſo practiſed them as they ought, which hath been as a Feaſt to thee, and ſuch as thee; and a grief to the tender and upright hearted; yet this doth not prove thoſe wholſom Inſtructions of Friends, (which thou ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly calls Order) <hi>bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>T.C. in the 2 page, ſaith, <hi>The Apoſtles ſaid, who have not the Spirit of Chriſt, are not his; therefore no wonder that they give ſuch black names, to them who cannot give up all</hi> their Faith and Conſciences to their Womens Meetings, hereby it is—<hi>proved that</hi> G. F'<hi>s, &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver ſal Spirit is not that of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and Ancient Friends
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108319:7"/>—therefore not the ſame, but a private Spirit or Party which adore him and his Laws, as</hi> S.E. <hi>and</hi> C.T. <hi>have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> T. C's wicked and ungodly Inſinuation as if Friends required people to give up <hi>all their Faith</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, to Womens Meetings, which is as much as if he ſaid, Friends required perſons to have no Faith in Chriſt, nor no Conſcience to deal juſtly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for if they muſt give up all to them, they leave none for any thing elſe, let the Reader now judge whether <hi>T. C.</hi> hath the Spirit of Chriſt, or is excited thereby thus to write, yea or nay that thus inſinuates, for though I believe Chriſt is ſerved in the Womens Meetings; and that they are according to his mind; yet I don't place <hi>All</hi> my Faith and Conſcience in them; neither doth this prove that <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> Univerſal Spirit (by which I take him to mean that Univerſal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>G. F.</hi> and Friends bear Teſtimony of and direct unto) is not the Spirit of Chriſt, the Apoſtles and Ancient Friends, but a private Spirit which adore him and his Laws, for I charge it upon <hi>T. C.</hi> as a grand untruth or a Lye. For T.C. to ſay S. E. and C.T. have ador'd or worſhip'd <hi>C. F.</hi> or his Laws; for I affirm all true and Spiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (which is the Worſhip we own) is only due unto God and Chriſt, and is performed in the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>T. C. in the 10th page, ſaith, That <hi>G. F. &amp;c. will not admit that any have the leaſt meaſure of the Spirit that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not to his Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> This is another of his untruths or Lies, for its well known he hath often teſtified unto the Univerſality of the Grace and Spirit of God, and hath ſaid with the Apoſtle that the manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal.</p>
            <p>In the 11th page, <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whereby it is manifeſt what high Eſteem and great Authority you Aſcribe to your Orders; that the bare obeying them, can Acquit in Gods ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> This is another of <hi>T. C</hi>'s great and palpable untruths or Lyes and <hi>Thomas</hi> prove if thou canſt that any owned by us ſo high Eſteem, and aſcribed ſuch great Authority to thoſe Good, Orders and wholſome Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions given by the Spirit of the Lord through his Servants concerning the outward Converſation and performance of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108319:8"/>things amongſt the People of God; which thou in diriſion commonly calls <hi>G. F.</hi> orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For we are of the Apoſtles mind that ſome may retain the form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and be out of, and Enimies to the power thereof and ſuch never were, nor are owned by the Lord God nor his faithful people, for Hypocriſy was and is an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto the Lord. And a blind Sacrifice was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under Law nor Goſpel owned by him, And they that have the form of Godlineſs, and are out of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Enimies to it, are not acquitted in Gods ſight for being in the form, neither can they that are Born of God, have Unity with them, that have the form of Godlineſs, and are out of the power thereof though we ſay its poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as it was in the Apoſtles days, that ſome may have the outward form of Godlineſs, to wit, a profeſſion of the Light, Grace, Spirit and Power of God, and yet be out of and Enimies to the ſame, but we know and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay, that they that walk in the Light, Spirit, Grace and power of God, the ſame gives them a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and accordingly leads them, in their Doctrine, life and Converſation, into a ſound Chriſtian form and order, for as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>God is the God of order and not of Confuſion, in all the Churches of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 20 T.C. ſaith, <hi>And for</hi> J.F. <hi>to ſay their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſtands in the Eternal Spirit it is falſe; for it is manifeſt to be in forms and needleſs Ceremonies: for ſuch as Conform and preach them up, have been, and are guilty of ſhameful Miſcarriages, and yet they are Suffered to continue as Preachers and no Judgment or Excommunication againſt them as out of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and they have received what they have given and Spent on them of others Eſtates, and not from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver ſal Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> This I Charge upon <hi>T. C.</hi> as a grand and fivefold untruth or Lye until he proves it, which I am well Satisfied he never can, though he would by this and ſuch like ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unchriſtian, and abominable falſhood, begett jealouſies in the mind of ſome againſt them that God hath raiſed up to publiſh his Truth, and that ſreely give up to ſpend and be ſpent in the Service of it and ſeek not any earthly thing, but the glory of God and Exaitation of his Truth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108319:8"/>according to their ſeveral meaſures and gifts and have a Teſtimony from God in their hearts againſt that lying Spirit that hath entred him and his Abettors which if he and they Repent not of, the plagues and Judgments of the Lords will certainly be their portion, to all Eternity for no Lyar can enter the Kingdom of God. For the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone, which is the ſecond Death, is their portion. Oh! that God may (if it be his Will) give <hi>T.C.</hi> and them a Heart to Repent before it's too late.</p>
            <p>In <hi>T. C</hi>'s Poſtſcript he ſaith, <hi>Alſo that grand falſhood of</hi> J. Feild's <hi>aſſerted in his Bull of diſowning me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Diſowning thee for my part, I have known thee ſome years, but never knew thou waſt owned by Friends, or the People called Quakers, or was one of them; for I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo looked upon thee I am ſure. <hi>T. C. alſo in his Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeript ſpeaks concerning the uſe of the word Company.</hi> And ſaith, <hi>Although the ſame uſed by</hi> G.F.J. Feild, S. Ecdes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Guilty of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note, J. Feild</hi> denysthat there is any ſuch word, <hi>viz.</hi> as <hi>(Company)</hi> in that he writ. And charges it upon thee among the many untruths that thou haſt writ concerning him and Friends, ſome (and but ſome) of which he hath here ſet down.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſay little more to this <hi>Babel</hi> Builder but ſet down the words of the paper (which he calls mine) and hath help't to fill his book with, (which he omitted) and ſhew how he hath perverted them, to make them ſpeak to his mind and <hi>Anſwer</hi> his corrupt end and vain Conceit, the words he left out are theſe <hi>viz.</hi> [Which leads all them that are faithful thereunto to be.]</p>
            <p>Now Read what he hath ſo often mentioned with theſe words to them as they were in that paper. And its thus. Friends unity and fellowſhip ſtands in that Etemal Spirit <hi>which leads all them that are faithful thereunto to be all</hi> of one mind and to ſpeake the ſame thing, and by the ſame Spirit a remnant, are Joyned together in the ſame mind and in the ſame Judgment among whom there is no Diviſion, and theſe with the one mind and mouth, glorify God, and ſerve him even the Father of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108319:9"/>our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with one mind and one accord <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pray now where's <hi>John Feuds</hi> falſe Aſſertion, or grand falſhood. For <hi>J.</hi> F. never ſaid <hi>T. C. W. R.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> &amp;c. were of one mind, for <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>The pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Cythes as at this day is Antichriſtian:</hi> but <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith <hi>Its his Principle to pay Tythes and Marry by a Prieſt,</hi> and hath practiced accordingly, in paying Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if <hi>J. F.</hi> had ſaid theſe were of one mind and Judgment and ſpake the ſame thing, <hi>T. C.</hi> might well have termed it falſe or a grand falſhood. Neither did <hi>J. F.</hi> ſay that thoſe that are not faithful to the Spirit of God were of one mind. And <hi>J. F.</hi> would not have <hi>T. C.</hi> ſay the Spirit of God is not at unity with it ſelf; nor that them that are led thereby not at Unity one with another; leaſt he thereby Contracts more guilt upon his Soul, and affirms that which he may (as for his other unfruitful words and works of darkneſs) have full ſore Cauſe to Repent of.</p>
            <p>So God who is large in his mercy and Infinite in his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (if it be his will) give him a heart to Repent of theſe his evil works, before he goes hence no more to be ſeen of man that they may not follow him and that theſe Sins (may not in that dreadful day, wherein God will Judge the Secrets of all hearts by Jeſus Chriſt according to his Goſpel, and reward every man according to his deeds) be ſuch a weight upon him, that will Sink him into the lake of endleſs miſery, and Horrible pit out of which there is no Redemption, for God who knows how to deliver the Righteous out of Temptation, knows how to Reſerve the wicked to the day of Judgement.</p>
            <p>Thomas Crisp. <hi>I am thy Friend who can and do (as I have learnt of Chriſt) freely forgive thee all thy hard ſpeeches and falſe ſayings concerning me.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lodnon,</hi> at the Bull and Mouth, <date>the 22 of the 1ſt month 1681/2.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Feild,</hi> Jun.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108319:9"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THere is one thing or two more that I before omitted and paſſed by as I have many other malicious words and falſhoods of <hi>T. Crisp</hi>'s for had I made a Catologue of them all, I am perſwaded they would have doubled if not trebled his pretended, 12 falſhoods ſet down in his Poſtſcript of the 4 part of Babels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his 16 and 17 page <hi>T. G. ſaith, But one Reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I paid: (that ſooften mentioned) as Tythes, was as a Witneſs that I was not taught my fear by the Precepts of</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c. nor receive his traditions for Doctrines, and that I had not Sacrificed all my faith Conſcience and Judgment to his Orders, your Idol to Worſhip, that as too many both ſmall and great do.—but as a Teſtimony againſt your Impoſitions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwera.</hi> Is not this an ungodly Inſinuation as if all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Friends that refuſe to pay Tythes (being ſo perſwaded of God in their Conſciences, and not from any outward Law or order) and <hi>therefore in the</hi> Lords will Suffer the Spoyle of their Goods and Impriſonment of their Bodies in Naſty Goals ſeperate from then render Wines Children and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milys, where many have ended their days in peace with God in their Chriſtian Teſtimony againſt that great op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Tythes, <hi>had Sacrificed all their faith, Conſcience and Judgement</hi> (to that <hi>T. C.</hi> ſcoffingly calls) <hi>G. F's orders, and that theſe are Friends Idol and they Worſhip</hi> them, Oh! the Lord rebuke thee thou lying Spirit read 120 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.3, 4. verſe. And prove <hi>T. Criſp</hi> if thou canſt any, of the many both ſmall and great that ſo do, <hi>viz.</hi> Worſhip <hi>G. F.</hi> Orders which thou <hi>Iſhmaelite</hi> like calls <hi>Friends Idol,</hi> or other wiſe Repent of (and as publickly confeſs Acknowledge and Condemn thy Envy falſhood and notoriouſly wicked Inſinuation as thou haſt publiſhed it, for we Abſolutely deny and diſown <hi>all Idols and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> to any Creature, or Created thing or outward order what ſoever, and have and do teach and profeſs all true and Spiritual Worſhip which is that we own, is due only
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108319:10"/>unto, God and Chriſt and performed in the holy Spirit. Yet we <hi>Anſwer</hi> the Apoſtle's Exhortation, and honour all men in the Lord and know them that Labour among us, and are over us in the Lord and admoniſh us, and do eſteem them very highly in Love for their Work ſake. Accounting the Elders that Rule well, worthy of double honour, eſpecially they that Labour in the Word and Doctrine, and againſt ſuch ſhall not receive thy lying accuſation, being Perſwaded (though they be accounted by thee and ſuch as thee, as the Apoſtles were by ſome <hi>viz.</hi> deceivers) yet they are true, and men that have hazarded their lives for the Goſpel and Teſtimony of Jeſus and have been in wants, in faſtings, in jeopardy, and perills by falſe Brethren and many wayes, whom God (bleſſed be his great and glorious name and holy power) hath hitherto preſerved and will unto the end, I firmly believe and Crown them with life and dominion and they ſhall (as many do) ſhine in the firmament of his power for ever and evermore notwithſtanding the Rage and Enmity of <hi>T. C.</hi> and ſuch as he, when (they if they Repent not,) <hi>for paine ſhall knaw their tongues,</hi> for God will certainly Judge thee for theſe wicked and hard ſpeeches, as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.11.</p>
            <p>But <hi>T. C</hi>'s heart is ſo filled with Enmity againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. that out of the aboundance thereof in his three ſheer and half he hath dotingly mentioned <hi>G.F</hi>'s name or the letters of it 134 times, and often ſpeaks Scoffingly and maliciouſly againſt <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Orders</hi> &amp;c. (as he calls them) but gives no Catalogue thereof, (though ſo highly offended at them) that others may Judge of them; only in his 16 page <hi>T.C.</hi> faith when any <hi>doth or denyeth any thing, not from Inwand Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, but becauſe,</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c. ſo order, or it is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom or practice of Friends: ſuch I call your orders, and do know there be too many ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> But this is no proof to me, for thou that haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed me and others, I am perſwaded follows the ſame trade or practice here, and I therefore Change it upon chee among the reſt as a deſigned and premeditated untouth, or lve, tilthou proves it by ſhewing who they are that ſo do, and what thoſe orders are</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108319:10"/>
            <p>And in the 12 page <hi>T. C.</hi> ſaith <hi>I Judge not nor Condemn any perſon for their Jugdment and practice, that differs from me, that is not breach, of the Revealed will</hi> of God, and have often Certified as much.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> well <hi>Thomas</hi> if this be thy Principle I deſire thee to ſhew and prove out of that Revealed will of God, what I (or Friends) ever writ, publiſhed, declared, or Exhorted to, that is a breach of that Revealed will of God, that thou haſt ſo Judged me (and them) as a falſe Witneſs and an Aſſertor of grand falſhood and an <hi>Inquiſition Officer, &amp;c.</hi> And till you ſo doſt, I Charge thee with grand falſhood and an Aſſertor thereof, alſo with the breach of thy owne Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which is grand Hypocriſy, and babiloniſh, Confuſion. Alſo prove that thy four Babels are according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. C.</hi> page 12. ſays <hi>R. R.</hi> is as one that has nothing to do but pick reaſons, becauſe I ſhewed him <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. their 12 reaſons for diſowning <hi>Barbados</hi> Paper; And though he ſays there's never a good one, yet he proves not the badneſs of any one, but only affirms, they are ſo; as if his authority, ſolely might ſtand for all reaſon (or rather withſtand it and truth too) and all muſt pin their faith on his ſleeve, notwithſtanding all reaſons to the contrary being wiſer in his own fooliſh conceit than ſeven wiſe men with all the reaſons they ſhall be able to render. And what ſhould one ſay to ſuch an unreaſonable conceited furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit (that ſeems to ſay, what have I to do with reaſon or Truth or peace, or thou either) but get thee behind me. Yet to ſhew the ſimple, whom he ſays he would undeceive, how good they are, compared with his,<note place="margin">Firſt Part Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Page.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe things are clearer by their oppoſites, and becauſe he diſproves not, but only compares and ſays there is a clearer diſowning than thoſe reaſons, ſo to make a ly. I ſhall pick a few of his or rather top the beſt of his basket, as he thinks belike, after the Example of ſuch chears; to ſhew the difference, that the ſimple may ſee they are ſo bad that they cannot be eaten, like the figgs the prophet ſaw;<note place="margin">Jer. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> as the other are very good, as they are found to be to ſuch as have not loſt their ſavour. And he ſhall bee content with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108319:11"/>his ſenſe, for brevityes ſake, and not ty us to his form in his many turnings windings and wriglings though he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly grumbles at <hi>S. C.</hi> for it,<note place="margin">Fourth Part, <hi>p. 1.</hi>
               </note> taking his ſence not very words. For he is more exact for words than matter, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them principles. Therefore <hi>T.C.</hi>'s reaſon that there's not one good one in all <hi>G.F.</hi> &amp;c. Their reaſons are firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>T. C.</hi> affirms it. And to prove that, he affirms that they are not good, becauſe there might be a better, not a clear diſowning becauſe there might be a clearer. He affirms it. And to prove that, he affirms that an affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is clearer than all reaſons, be they neaver ſo many and cogent, to make his own prefer'd before reaſons. And becauſe I ſay not ſo too, he calls me lyer, and other diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful terms, as he would make them ſeem, though elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he conſeſſes them an honour. And to confirm that, he implyes, for I take not his Very many words, but his matter and ſence, though he takes my words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my ſenſe, and wreſts them, as if he were ſenſeleſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched or fooliſh at beſt, and he ſeems to argue as if all the Apoſtles reaſons in that large letter were not a clear diſowning their following falſe Apoſtles and diſowning him, becauſe he called them Brethren and Churches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Would not ſuch an Apoſtate, turn againſt the true Apoſtles, and following the falſe, and holding up thoſe that hold the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and of the <hi>Nicolations</hi> or <hi>Libertins,</hi> have reaſoned thus againſt the true Apoſtles in that day. And would not the true Apoſtles be ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned againſt if they were in this day? But if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had been of his minde, principle, or principles if he will have it,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>6.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> againſt reaſons; he would not have taken ſo much pains to have given ſo many reaſons in a large letter writ with his own hand. But he was neither againſt good reaſons, noragainſt good orders; for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares Churh-Government to houſhold-Government, or ſteward-ſhip.<note place="margin">Pit <hi>1.7.</hi>
               </note> And in that ſcience tis a Maxim or rule. That evills detected and only rejected, and only reproved, and not diſproved do hurt. And they cannot be diſproved without reaſons againſt them. And becauſe <hi>T.C</hi>'s have been not only detected and rejected, but reproved and alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by reaſons; therefore he turnes againſt reaſons; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108319:11"/>mee as picking them, and turns to affirming it a freſh with out reaſon againſt me, page 12 after he has denyed he had done it to <hi>S. C.</hi> page 1. only holding againſt me that a bare reproof is clearer diſowning than reaſons, with his reaſon aforeſaid, falſely ſo called, indeed fallacyes, that is lyes in plaine Engliſh, diſſering only in form from his other confuſions and contradictions and wreſtings of my words. As like Papiſts, he makes Papiſts, as if like were the ſame, Churches he makes a Church; and the univerſal Spirit; the error of that one Church. That which is of god, he confounds with the perſon that is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it, and that of the beaſt with the perſon turned to it. Promiſe that is, of his party, he makes his own promiſe, to make up a ly. My words [Any of our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings] he makes any that have been in our Meetings (as himſelf and other ſuch) ſo implicitly charging all, in naming none, by his vagrant expreſſions and ſo wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in that which is of more value, than many oxen <hi>viz.</hi> the reputation of truth, which he turns againſt, evidently here joining with thoſe he ſaith we call heathens, againſt our Meetings and miniſters. This in ſhort to ſhew, how in his <hi>Babels</hi> he confounds generalls and particulars, ſame kind and ſeyerall kindes, one and more to compound his lyes, other whiles ſeperating things of the ſame kind to make them ſeverall, to make other lyes; as principle, he makes principles, and ſeverall I could produce, but to make him make another lye, <hi>viz.</hi> that I haven othing to do but pick lyes But becauſe he called on me for it to ſhew him them, I have taken ſome time to ſhew him and the Reader a few of many his lyes reaſons or fallacys, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and Confuſions (in his <hi>Bables</hi>) his principles, if her will have it ſo; though they be of one kind unleſs he will deny it, and ſay Nay, they are not all of one kind, for they are not all mine; For Bacon is not ſwine that tramples all &amp; turns and rends; and give that as a principle among his next reaſons. And then let him prove his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons good ones, before he call <hi>[Iſhmael]</hi> again, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the promiſe ſeed, not that deſpiſed <hi>Bable-builders</hi> and <hi>Baals-Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> that deſerved it, as their due, and his, and that which he ſooften calls for <hi>viz.</hi> fools
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108319:12"/>and bewitched, and let him as often take it, ſeeing he preferrs ſharp reproof before reaſons and reſt with it, if he will, and let me reſt, as I deſire and reſolve in the Lords ſtrength, accounting it an honour, (as he confeſſes it to be) to continue a ſervant for ever to the Lord and his Truth, and therein in love to thoſe that continue for ever the ſervants of the Lord and his truth out of the Apoſtacy, and enmity to it and them, but oppoſit to its enemy the Prince of Darkneſs, the deſtroying beaſt that Rages, now <hi>T. C.</hi> his preſent principle he joins to, in his work, not to his or any mans perſon, but a Friend of that and all that's of God <hi>R. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In taxing me with a ly, for making him as never find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that England groaned under the Pope in Temporals, becauſe he ſays the Pope never gained the point <hi>Barbados</hi> paper did, he does but prove himſelf in the ly, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and confuſion, which is all one what ever he would make them. Or elſe he muſt ſay that the Pope never gained the pointin Spirituals, which moſt know to be a ly, and he and his abetters againſt their perſwaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in accuſe <hi>G.F.</hi> &amp;c. falſely of Popery and alſo maliciouſly, for the Pope in Spirtual and Temporals too gained what he ſought, which they neither ſought nor gained. For ſince the writing hereof I have read a letter from <hi>Barbados</hi> the 14 of the 11 month 1681. ſubſcribed by Fifteen Friends there in behalf of the Meeting (which I have to produce) and here inſert an Abſtract of an acount from the Quarterly Meeting at <hi>Barbado's</hi> of what paſt there, and the Judgment of the paper excepted againſt both before and after the Advice from Friends at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How that it was <hi>Judged with general conſent the next quarterly Meeting after called their yearly Meeting</hi> 1 <hi>ſt month</hi> 81. <hi>Several months before any notice from any other place touching it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſe in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>Letter</hi> are their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they fo we, or their for our, <hi>&amp;c</hi> uſed for abbreviation.</note> Before which time, of giving publick notice of the ſame to have a good underſtanding, that it might be rectifyed, ſome <hi>gained it or rather part of it, and ſent abroad privately with diſlike, contrary to truth and its order with them. But it was aften Judged,</hi> as aforeſaid <hi>and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be taken out of</hi> their <hi>Quarterly Meeting Book.</hi> And they declere that eyen <hi>ſome Moderate men of the World in that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108319:12"/>I ſtand</hi> were grieved that the <hi>Apoſtles advice was not hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end to</hi> (1 Cor. 6.) <hi>by ſome.</hi> And that the <hi>Copy</hi> that went abroad was <hi>wrong</hi> and not according to the <hi>ſenſe of the meeting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">That is, that they who are come to ſuch loſs might yet hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants, and Church of Chriſt, and not go to Law one with another.</note> viz. <hi>whether you will give up to your own particulars only, that is, thoſe particular Judgments which have or were come unto a loſs in themſelves, or have loſt their beloved,</hi> Cant. 1.7, 8. <hi>as the Scriptures teſtify and was ſpoke to in the Meeting. But was never in their hearts: to preſs their publick Judgment againſt any particular meaſure of the Spirit of God in any particular, but to be helpful to the dimſighted,</hi> &amp;c. and that they are <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> for their <hi>ſhortneſs where in</hi> they <hi>have grieved any,</hi> and are <hi>ſatisfyed there is no need of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward tye, or ſubſcription.</hi> And <hi>that the Judgment of any men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cut of the univerſal Spirit and meaſure of true light re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Chriſt, ought not to rule and Govern,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but the Spinit and Wiſdom of God alone, and the contrary Judged by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby appears to the unprejudiced Reader how unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and unſeaſonable, the <hi>ſharp reproof, fooliſh, bewitched, &amp;c.</hi> that <hi>T.C.</hi> ſo furiouſly calls for, had been; when as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the advice came to them they were ſenſible of their <hi>ſnortneſs,</hi> though they had aimed at the beſt, to bring to the Apoſtles advice thoſe that were contentious about outward things even to the offence of the world alſo. And how greedily that Spirit in <hi>T. C.</hi> and others here and there alſo gapes to have that Church devoured, calling, ſo eagerly for <hi>ſharp reproof, withſtanding to the face, calling fools, bewitched,</hi> &amp;c. And judging that which was already judged. Nay <hi>T. C.</hi> is ſo forward, and furious that he proceeds aforehand, before having writen or ſpoken to them to know the Truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.15.</note> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did to Judge with that which is to be Judged, and alſo to publiſh and print contrary to the promiſe of his Abetter and after the Example of <hi>W. R.</hi> who againſt and contrary to the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Truth, leaves out that principle in point of Judgment. And Part 4. page 31. cites (but quotes not the Book and Part, for then his materal omiſſions might eaſily be found out) ſome of <hi>G. F</hi>'s words in the beginning of a letter to all Friends, in the end of a Book of his titled, ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Papers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Printed 1671 <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:108319:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> [cites Judge not one another] But omits, [Judge not with that which muſt be Judged] the ſubſtance mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and principle,<note n="*" place="margin">And judge Pelf forſt, and you that ſee clear, ſpeak to the other whoſe munds are gone fron: the Light.</note> Elſe If one have ſpoken to, admoniſhed or Judged the evil in any one never ſo often to their face, yet they muſt not ſpeake of it on any occaſion, though it be to their own vindication, and clearing of the Truth, unleſs the party be preſent, but muſt ly under it, till he procure the party to come to hear it, though having heard it never ſo often before and withſtood it. This would bar telling the Church, unleſs and untill he can gett the other to come with him there, if the words muſt be taken only in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, reſtraming all ſpeaking in any caſe from any ground or principle againſt the abſem, when ſelf is firſt judged down. Which <hi>T. C.</hi> would have ſtand, and be a Judge of principles and practices and a ſharp reprover (page 14) But would not have the Beaſt, the Deſtroyer <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apollyon,</hi> the Curſed Spirit ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan diſcouered and Judged where he had entred. But thoſe that aiming at the beſt things, the Apoſtles advice, though coming ſhort in ſome thing and Judging it in themſelves before they are ſpoke to or Judged by others. Thoſe are they that <hi>T. C.</hi> and ſuch as he, have ſpread the weakneſs of, and Judged behind their backs with that which is to be Judged, and would have withſtood to the face that do not withſtand; but with the Wiſdom of God Judge the fooliſhneſs they were bewitched into (if he will needs have it) upon the firſt diſcovery before they were writ to, which wee do not read the <hi>Galatians</hi> did, but go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the fleſh and them that ſought to glory in it, from the Spirit and him that miniſtred it to them, and the naditions it led into, which the Churches keept and good order of the Goſpel in their Churches,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.15. and 3.6.</note> as it doth now, which you clancour againſt in generall, becauſe it ſeems, you would have people believe they were other than they are, and therefore are aſhamed of producing a Catalogue of them in particular, ſo often called for, but cry only in general <hi>G. Fox's</hi> Orders, Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and tells not what they are.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Richardſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108319:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
